Guide to the Land of Zenj Photograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Land of Zenj photograph collection
1869-2006
1869-1937
GEN MSS 619
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.85
(26 boxes)
The collection, assembled by the rare book dealers Jenny Allsworth and Humphrey Winterton, brings together photographs, photograph albums, glass lantern slides, and a lantern projector, which document the Sultanate of Zanzibar and European colonial expansion in East and Central Africa from 1870 to 1914. Also documented are early Arab and Portuguese coastal settlements at Kilwa, Mafia, Pemba, Sofala, and Zanzibar. The collection also represents the work of certain photographers who operated in different parts of the region, including C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam, Coutinho Brothers of Zanzibar and Dar es Salaam, P. De Lord Brothers of Zanzibar and Dar es Salaam, Walther Dobbertin, and A. C. Gomes & Co. of Zanzibar, among others.
Allsworth, Jenny
Winterton, Humphrey
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Allsworth Rare Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The Land of Zenj
The Land of Zenj refers to the Arab-controlled region of East Africa, in particular the coastal area, once known as the Zenj Empire. This region flourished for five hundred years from its inception in the 10th century until its demise at the hands of the Portuguese in the early 16th century. The Omani Arabs assumed control of the region from the Portuguese in the 18th century. In 1832, the Iman of Oman, Seyyid Said bin Sultan, made Zanzibar the capital of his East African empire. The opening of the Suez Canal in 1869 led to renewed European interest in the region, and by the early 1890s, Germany, Great Britain, and Portugal were competing for control over different areas within the region. The former Land of Zenj eventually came to comprise the British Protectorates of East Africa, Uganda and Zanzibar (the latter including Mombasa and the rest of the Coastal Strip), British Central Africa, German East Africa, and most of Portuguese East Africa.
Scope and Contents
The collection, assembled by the rare book dealers Jenny Allsworth and Humphrey Winterton, brings together photographs, photograph albums, glass lantern slides, and a lantern projector, which document the Sultanate of Zanzibar and European colonial expansion in East and Central Africa from 1870 to 1914. Also documented are early Arab and Portuguese coastal settlements at Kilwa, Mafia, Pemba, Sofala, and Zanzibar. The collection also represents the work of certain photographers who operated in different parts of the region, including C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam, Coutinho Brothers of Zanzibar and Dar es Salaam, P. De Lord Brothers of Zanzibar and Dar es Salaam, Walther Dobbertin, and A. C. Gomes & Co. of Zanzibar, among others.
Arrangement
The collection has been intellectually organized into eight series: I. Allsworth Rare Books Catalog, 2006; II. Individual Albums and Custom-Boxed Sets, 1880-1927; III. Panoramas and Photographers' Portfolios, 1880-1910; IV. Thematic Collections, 1875-1925; V. People, 1890-1900; VI. Ports and Other Places, 1885-1920; VII. Magic Lantern Slides, 1895-1910; and VIII. The Voyage Out (and Back) Through the Suez Canal, 1869-1937.
This series arrangement reflects the way in which the material is logically organized in the dealer catalog.
Oversize material from all series has been physically organized together in Boxes 16-26. Oversize material is described below in the series of which it forms part intellectually with a note about its physical location, as well as in the listing of oversize boxes.
Blacks -- Africa -- Pictorial works; Whites -- Africa -- Pictorial works; Africa -- Pictorial works; Dar es Salaam (Tanzania) -- Pictorial works; German East Africa -- Pictorial works; Zanzibar -- Pictorial works; Lantern slides; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Projectors; A. C. Gomes & Co; C. Vincente (Firm); Coutinho Bros; Pereira de Lord Brothers; Walther Dobbertin (Firm)
- Allsworth Rare Books Catalog, 2006; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  - "The Land of Zenj. The Sultanate of Zanzibar and European Colonial Expansion into East and Central Africa, 1870-1914. An Historical Photographic Record compiled and catalogued, with commentary and annotations, by Jenny Allsworth and Humphrey Winterton."
    - "Volume One. Pre-amble and Chapter One (with relative illustrations).", 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      This volume provides detailed descriptive information about the collection as a whole and about the material found in Series II of this finding aid.
    - "Volume Two. Chapter Two - Seven (with relative illustrations).", 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      This volume provides detailed descriptive information about the material found in Series III-VIII of this finding aid.
- Individual albums and custom-boxed sets, 1880-1927; Series II; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter One of the dealer of the catalog.
  - British East Africa: 1 photograph album, 1904-1905 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    A private snapshot album recording a year's stay, based in Nairobi, by the compiler "C.M.C." and her husband "R.J.C." from November 1904 to November 1905 and containing forty-nine images of various small sizes.
  - British East Africa and Uganda Protectorates: 1 photograph album, circa 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Album containing sixty original photographs by unidentified photographers, although some may be the work of William D. Young.
  - East Africa, Zanzibar and Aden: 1 photograph album, 1904
    An album containing twenty-four original photographs and one colored print, all captioned in French and recording scenes on a voyage from Lourenço Marques to Aden, with stops at Dar es Salaam, Tanga, Zanzibar, and Mombasa, in early 1904.
  - Eastern Africa: 1 photograph album, circa 1904-1907
    An album containing thirty-nine original photographs and twenty-one postcards, which document an extended visit to Zanzibar, Dar es Salaam, Tanga, Mombasa, Portuguese East Africa, and Durban. Some of the captions are dated, variously between March 1904 and January 1907.
  - Eastern and Central Africa. Mr. and Mrs. Walter Draper, circa 1903-1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    A portfolio of one hundred and twenty-two original photographs and two postcards compiled by the missionaries, Mr. and Mrs. Walter Draper, between 1903 and 1927. The images document the life and work at several different mission stations and leprosy colonies in the area.
  - German East Africa: 1 photograph album, circa 1896-1910
    An album entitled "Kamera Bilder aus Deutschostafrika", apparently produced by Walther Dobbertinm Daressalam. Images date from circa 1896 to 1910, documenting all aspects of life in the early years of recently formed German colony on the African Equator.
  - German East Africa, circa 1896-1913
    A collection of two hundred and thirty-five original photographs, mostly snapshots, housed in two albums and one custom-made box. Photographs by an unidentified photographer, dating from 1896 to 1913 and documenting the life of German soldiers and settlers in a recently established colony with a focus on upcountry military and farming life, particularly in Usumbara and the northwestern Kilimanjaro area around Moshi.
    - 62 photographs (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
    - 1 photograph album, circa 1898-1910
    - 1 photograph album, circa 1896-1913 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Portuguese East Africa and the British Central African Protectorate: 1 photograph album, 1904-1909
    An album apparently compiled by "C.L.W" and containing images of the construction of the Shire Highlands Railway, as well as scenic views, images of a big game hunting safari, and two images of the grave of Dr. Livingstone's wife, Mary Moffat, at Shupunga.
  - Portuguese East Africa, Zanzibar, Aden: 1 photograph album, circa 1880
    Thirteen albumen prints, with captions, recording a sea voyage up the east coast of Africa from Portuguese East Africa via Zanzibar and Aden.
  - Portuguese East Africa, Mozambique: 38 photographs with related printed material, 1886-1911
    A portfolio of thirty-eight original photographs, mostly by named photographers and dating from 1886 to 1911. Images portray diverse aspects of and different places in the Portuguese colony.
  - Winston Churchill's Big-Game Safari in Uganda in 1907, 1907, 1915
    An album compiled by Lieutenant C. E. Fishbourne, documenting a big-game hunting safari in Uganda undertaken by Winston Churchill in 1907, on which Fishbourne served as an escort, and including images of Churchill and other members of the party. Accompanying material includes a letter of condolence from Churchill written upon the death of Fishbourne in 1915.
    - Uganda: 1 photograph album, 1907-1908
    - Churchill, Winston and others: correspondence, 1908-1915 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Zanzibar and Pemba: 1 photograph album, 1896-1913
    An album containing sixty-eight original photographs and one panoramic postcard, dating from 1896 to 1913 and containing views of ruined mosques and mosque interiors, views of Pemba and Zanzibar town, and ngoma images.
  - Zanzibar and German East Africa: 20 albumen prints, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
    A series of photographs entitled "Erinnerung an die Deutsch-Afrikanische Messe den 6 und 7 März, 1895. Zum besten des Militär-Hilfsvereins."
  - Zanzibar. Hansing & Co.
    A series of four albums compiled by a member of the Zanzibar branch of the Hamburg trading house of Hansing & Co., accompanied by five loose photographs
    - Album A: 1 photograph album, circa 1909-1912
    - Album B: 1 photograph album, circa 1909-1912 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Album C: 1 photograph album, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Album D: 1 photograph album, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Loose photographs, 1910-1911 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Panoramas and Photographers' Portfolios, 1880-1910; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter Two of the dealer catalog.
  - Panoramas, circa 1880s-1910
    Includes panoramas of Dar es Salaam, Lourenço Marques, Mombasa, Pangani, Tanga, and Zanzibar.
  - Photographer's Portfolios
    - Coutinho Brothers-Zanzibar: 20 photographs, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
      A series of twenty images of diverse views and scenes of Zanzibar by Coutinho Brothers, Photographers of Main Road, Zanzibar. Images are unmounted and mostly captioned on the verso in English or German.
    - Coutinho Brothers-Dar es Salaam: 18 photographs, circa 1897-1900 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
      A series of eighteen original photographs of Dar es Salaam by Coutinho Brothers, Photographers of Main Road, Zanzibar and of Dar es Salaam. Images are unmounted and with manuscript captions on the verso.
    - P. De Lord Brothers - Dar es Salaam and Zanzibar, circa 1890s
      Twenty-four original photographs of scenes and views in Dar es Salaam and Zanzibar by P. De Lord Brothers, Photographers, Zanzibar.
    - Walther Dobbertin - German East Africa, circa 1902-1910 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      A series of twelve unmounted, original photographs, all untitled, by Walther Dobbertin, Post Buchholz, Kreis Hamburg, each bearing Dobbertin's stamp on the verso.
    - [Walther Dobbertin?] - German East Africa, circa 1890
      Four large mounted, original photographs by unidentified photographer, which may be the work of Walther Dobbertin.
    - A. C. Gomes & Co. - Zanzibar: 18 photographs, circa 1890-1900 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
      A series of eighteen original photographs depicting aspects of life in Zanzibar in the 1890s and early 1900s by A. C. Gomes & Co., Zanzibar; each are stamped with some manuscript identifications on the verso.
    - J. and J. & M. Lazarus-Portuguese East Africa, circa 1900-1910 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      A series of eleven original photographs by J. Lazarus or J. & M. Lazarus, and mostly of Lourenço Marques, Beira and Sofala.
    - K. Ledermann-Zanzibar: 6 photographs, circa 1880
      A series of six original photographs by K. Ledermann, Zanzibar with captions and mounted in pairs on the recto and verso of thick card, disbound album leaves.
    - A. Monteiro-German East Africa: 6 photographs, circa 1890-1900 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      Six original photographs of A. Monteiro, Photographer Dar-es Salaam, unmounted and mostly uncaptioned.
    - R. V. Periera-Tanga and German East Africa: 10 photographs, circa 1900, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
      A series of ten original photographs, all stamped "R. V. Periera, Photographer, Tanga, D. O. Africa" on the verso.
    - C. Vincenti-Portfolio of trees, bushes, plants and crops, circa 1896-1910 (Box 5, Folder 30-35)
      A portfolio of botanical images all identified as being by, or attributed to, C. Vincenti of Dar es Salaam and dated from 1896 to 1910. The portfolio comprises a series of studies of some of the trees, fruits, and crops indigenous to the coastal area of German East Africa, together with agricultural crops such as sisal, sugar and tobacco which were introduced.
- Thematic collections, 1875-1925; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Material in this series corresponds to that described in Chapter Three of the dealer catalog.
  Arrangement
  Photographs arranged thematically by the dealer.
  - Zanzibar - Four sultans and a would-be usurper: 8 photographs (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - 1. Seyyid Barghash bin Said - A group cabinet portrait, on the original photographers' card mount. Maull & Co. of London., 1875; 11 x 16 cm.
    - 2. Seyyid Hamed bin Thuwaini - "Late Sultan. Before Bombardment 1896." Coutinho Brothers, Main Road, Zanzibar., 1893; 29.5 x 21 cm., mounted on card
    - 3. Seyyid Hamed bin Thuwaini, Portrait. [Coutinho Brothers?], 1893; 21 x 28 cm, 36.5 x 46.5 cm. mounted
    - 4. Seyyid Khalid bin Barghash, Portrait, unmounted and stamped on verso "E. C. Dias, photographer, Zanzibar", 1893; 13 x 18.5 cm.
    - 5. Seyyid Ali bin Hamoud, Group Portrait. Unidentified photographer., 1905; 20 x 14.5 cm.
      On verso: Zanzibar. Effects of Bombardment. Unidentified photographer, 1896 from Zanzibar - The Sultans' Palaces.
    - 6. Seyyid Khalifa bin Haroub, Group Portrait. Unidentified photographer., circa 1913; 24 x 19 cm.
    - 7 and 8. Seyyid Khalifa bin Haroub, Two postcard portrait images. De Lord Brothers and Gomes & Co., circa 1920, circa 1925; 14 x 9 cm. each
  - Zanzibar-The Sultan's palaces: 37 photographs
    General note
    Photograph numbers correspond to those from the dealer catalog.
    - Before August, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - 1. "General view of Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer. Mounted on thick card, disbound, album leaf., circa 1880; 20.3 x 13.5 cm., 40 x 30 cm. mounted
      - 2. "Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., 1880s; 21 x 15 cm.
      - 3. "Alter Sultanspalast Zanzibar." Coutinho Brothers, Photographers, Main Road, Zanzibar., 1890s; 20.5 x 14.4 cm.
      - 4. "Altes Haremsgebaüde in Zanzibar." Coutinho Brothers, Photographers, Main Road, Zanzibar., 1890s; 21 x 14.5 cm.
      - 5. "Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 23 x 17 cm.
      - 6. "Sultans Palast in Zanzibar," mounted on card with pencilled title in the lower margins. Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 20.5 x 15 cm.
      - 7. "Sultans Palast in Zanzibar," mounted on card with pencilled title in the lower margins. Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 20.5 x 15 cm.
      - 8. "Zanzibar. Sultans Palace" with caption "8 Sultan's Harem with Tower A.", circa 1890; 20.3 x 14.5 cm.
      - 9. The Sultan's Palace complex, pre-bombardment, from the sea, with the Sultan's launch passing in front. Unidentified photographer., circa 1895; 19.5 x 14 cm.
      - 10. Zanzibar Palace. Unidentified photographer (possibly Coutinho Brothers)., 1896; 29 x 21 cm.
      - 11. Sultan's Palace, Zanzibar. Unidentified photographer., circa 1895; 23 x 17 cm.
    - The British Bombardment and "The Shortest War in History", 1896 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      Includes original photographs depicting the damage and destruction caused to the Sultan's Palace by the British Naval Bombardment on 27 August 1896.
      - 12. Sultan's Palace, Zanzibar, shortly after the British Bombardment. Unidentified photographer., 1896; 20 x 14.5 cm.
      - 13. The Sultan's Palace complex in the immediate aftermath of the Bombardment. Unidentified photographer, 1896; 20.5 x 14.5 cm.
      - 14. "Alter Sultanspalast in Zanzibar nach der...[?]...durch dies Engländer 189[6]" Coutinho Brothers, Photographers, Main Road, Zanzibar., 20.5 x 14.7 cm.
      - 15. "Theil des Sultanpalastes...Engländer Zanzibar. Ost Afrika." Unidentified photographer., 1896; 20.5 x 15 cm.
      - 16. "Zanzibar Palace Bombardment." Unidentified photographer., 1896; 21.3 x 15 cm.
      - 17. "Sultan's Palace...[?]..." Unidentified photographer., 1896; 20.8 x 15 cm.
      - 18. "Zanzibar. Effects of Bombardment." Unidentified photographer., 1896; 28.5 x 21 cm.
        On recto: Seyyid Ali bin Hamoud, Group Portrait. Unidentified photographer from Zanzibar - Four sultans and a would-be usurper.
      - 19. Zanzibar. Effects of Bombardment. Unidentified photographer., 1896; 29 x 20.5 cm.
    - The Rebuilt Palace (Box 6, Folder 39)
      - 20. "Zanzibar, Sultanspalast." Unidentified photographer., circa 1898; 20 x 15 cm.
      - 21. Sultan's Palace, Zanzibar. Unidentified photographer., circa 1897; 15 x 10 cm.
      - 22. Sultan's Palace, Zanzibar, rebuilt after the bombardment of 1896. Coutinho Brothers., circa 1900; 21 x 14 cm.
      - 23. The Beit el-Ajaib or House of Wonders. A. C. Gomes & Co., circa 1904; 20.5 x 14.5 cm.
      - 24. "Throne room of Sultan's palace, Zanzibar, E. Africa." Glass lantern slide. Underwood & Underwood, Beit el-Ajaib., circa 1900; 10 x 8 cm.
      - 25. "Neuer Sultanspalast (Zanzibar)." Coutinho Brothers, Photographers, Main Road, Zanzibar., circa 1900; 21.3 x 15 cm.
      - 26. Untitled. Coutinho Brothers, Photographers, Dar es Salaam., circa 1910; 15.4 x 11 cm.
      - 27. "Zanzibar Roadstead, Sultan's Palace." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 19 x 14 cm.
        Part of Zanzibar album pages that are bound with string.
    - Palace Parades and Ceremonies (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - 28. "In front of the Sultan's Palace Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 20 x 15 cm.
      - 29. [German caption]. Unidentified photographer., circa 1885-1890; 21 x 15 cm.
      - 30. "M'haji Moja Street, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1890s; 18.8 x 14.1 cm.
      - 31. "Mazi Moja Street, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1890s; 15.2 x 10.6 cm.
      - 32. "Sultan's Troops, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1890s; 21.4 x 14.6 cm.
      - 33. "Sultan's Procession." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1890s; 23.7 x 14.4 cm.
      - 34. "Anniversary of Sultan, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1890s; 22.4 x 15.5 cm.
      - 35. "H. H. The Sultan of Zanzibar leaving the Palace in State." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 20.5 x 14.5 cm.
      - 36. Zanzibar. Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 21.6 x 15.3 cm.
  - Slave-trade in East Africa: 9 photographs (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - 1. Arab Slave Traders in the Congo. Unidentified photographer., 1887; 16 x 21 cm.
    - 2. Rumaliza & Söhne. Annotated in German on verso. C. Vincente., 1897; 16.5 x 22.8 cm.
    - 3. "Slave Prisoners, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., Zanzibar., circa 1890; 20.5 x 15 cm.
    - 4. "Slaves rescued from Arab dhow near Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 20 x 13.5 cm.
    - 5. Zanzibar, Untitled. Unidentified photographer., circa 1875-1880; 19 x 13 cm.
    - 6. [German caption]. Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 21.2 x 15.5 cm.
    - 7. "Prisoners with water cart, Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 20 x 15 cm.
    - 8. "Karawane für - Innere Ost Afrika - Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 20.4 x 14.5 cm.
    - 9. "A group of porters - also prisoners in chains at Bagamoyo." Unidentified photographer., circa 1890; 20 x 15 cm.
  - The U. M. C. A. [Universities Mission to Central Africa] and the emancipation of slaves in Zanzibar: 12 photographs (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - 1. The Anglican Cathedral, Zanzibar. A. C. Gomes & Co., Photographers, Zanzibar., circa 1900; 20.5 x 14.5 cm.
    - 2. "Zanzibar Church." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 15.2 x 10.2 cm.
    - 3. "Interior of the Slave Market Church." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 18.5 x 14 cm.
    - 4. "Slave Market Church and Bishop's House." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
    - 5. "Boys School. Künua Mzuu. Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 19.5 x 13 cm.
    - 6. "Bishop's House & Infant Boys' School. Zanzibar." Unidentified photographer., circa 1880; 17 x 13 cm.
    - 7. "English Mission Zanzibar.", 20.3 x 14 cm.
    - 8. Untitled [A group portrait of U. M. C. A. mission "boys" and five missionaries]., 21 x 15.8 cm.
    - 9. "Freed slaves at Mbweni with Miss Thackeray.", 17.5 x 12.2 cm.
    - 10. Untitled. A Cabinet Portrait by Carlton & Sons of Horncastle., 1880s; 10.3 x 14.7 cm.
    - 11 and 12. Untitled. Two snapshots mounted on card.
  - Other East African churches and missions: 40 photographs (Box 6, Folder 43-45)
    - 1. "Pères Blancs, Zanzibar." A. C. Gomes & Co., 1897; 26.8 x 16.8 cm.
    - 2. "C. M. S. Hospital buildings, Mombasa E. Africa." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 14.2 x 10 cm.
    - 3. "Mission Bagamoyo." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 17 x 12.5 cm.
    - 4. "Schwester Lies der Mission Bagamoyo." Unidentified photographer., 1890s; 17.5 x 12.2 cm.
    - 5. "Kath. Mission in Tanga." Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 18 x 12 cm.
    - 6. "Musikkapelle, Tanga." R. V. Pereira, Photographer, Tanga, D. O. Africa., circa 1900; 21 x 15.5 cm.
    - 7. "[?]...in Daressalaam." R. V. Pereira, Photographer, Tanga, D. O. Africa., circa 1900; 20.8 x 15 cm.
    - 8. "Evangelische Missionstation Tanga." R. V. Pereira, Photographer, Tanga, D. O. Africa., circa 1900; 21 x 15.5 cm.
    - 9. Untitled with annotations in German on verso. Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 21 x 15 cm.
    - 10. Untitled with annotations on verso. Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 20.8 x 15.5 cm.
    - 11. "Vue de la Mission de Buhonga du coté du Tanganica et Congo." Unidentified photographer., circa 1898; 17 x 11.5 cm.
    - 12. "Enfants Warundi...de Marienheim (Ubuhonga)." Unidentified photographer., 1903
    - 13. "...Mission...van Thiel...Marienberg mit 6...22.12.99" Unidentified photographer., 1899; 17 x 12.2 cm.
    - 14. "Marien - Seen (Kunyinya)." Unidentified photographer., 1906; 13 x 9 cm.
    - 15. "Die See Rwagwa bei Mariensee." Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 14 x 6.4 cm.
    - 16. "Inhangi Ruanda." Unidentified photographer., circa 1900; 17 x 12.5 cm.
    - 17. "...Station Usambara." Unidentified photographer., circa 1905; 11 x 8 cm.
    - 18. "Missionschwestern in Kiborcho. Trapistenorder aus Natal." Unidentified photographer., circa 1905; 6 x 8.5 cm.
    - 19. "Mission Kiborcho." Unidentified photographer., circa 1905; 8.5 x 6 cm.
    - 20. "Crocodile Pool Kisilutini E. Africa." Unidentified photographer., late 1880s; 15.3 x 11.7 cm.
    - 21. "C. M. S. Station Kisilutini E. Africa." Unidentified photographer., late 1880s; 15.7 x 11.5 cm.
    - 22. "Group of Natives Kisilutini E. Africa." Unidentified photographer., late 1880s; 7 x 10 cm.
    - 23. "Native sewing class Kisilutini E. Africa." Unidentified photographer., late 1880s; 15.6 x 11 cm.
    - 24. "Ev. Mission Hoffnungshöhe." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1897; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 25. "Ev. Mission Hoffnungshöhe" [Another view]. C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1897; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.
    - 26. "Hoffnungshöhe, Kirche." C. Vicente of Dar es Salaam., 1898; 23.5 x 17.5 cm.